

#### ASTROPHYSICS RESEARCHER . GALAXY FORMATION & EVOLUTION

41 Amulet Crescent, Richmond Hill, L4S2V8, Ontario, Canada

🛘 (+1) 647-221-0865 | 💌 juanpabloalfonzo@protonmail.com | 🏕 juanpabloalfonzo.github.io | 🖸 juanpabloalfonzo | 🛅 juan-pablo-alfonzo-7b9623201

# Summary\_

My research lies in the area of **galaxy evolution and formation** within astrophysics. My research area in particular is very programming/computationally heavy. I like describing my area of research as an **intersection between astronomy and computer science**, specifically **machine learning and data science**. A lot of the work I have done and hope to continue doing heavily involves programming and using Python based algorithms. These algorithms have a heavy emphasis on machine learning and **artificial neural networks** to help answer research questions associated with galaxy evolution and formation. Along with this, my current research is expanding to also involve **programming theoretical physics models into a computational simulation** to test them against observed data.

# Research Experience \_\_\_\_\_\_

University of Toronto Toronto, Canada

SURP RESEARCHER/ RESEARCH ASSISTANT

May 2021 - Present

- Working on training a convolutional neural network (CNN) to classify galaxies in the MaNGA survey, while studying what features of the galaxies the neural network is focusing on to make the classification.
- · Network being created and trained using the pytorch Python package and working in a Linux based environment
- Final goal is to have the CNN be able to predict the star forming history of the galaxies from their visual image and spectral information. Aim to not only having a working CNN but to be able to pick it apart to understand how it is making decisions and extract relevant physics
- Project Supervisor: Dr. Kathreik Iyer (Dunlap Institute)

University of Toronto Toronto, Canada

Undergraduate Researcher Aug. 2020 - Apr. 2021

- · Investigated morphological changes in galaxies as they evolve in time, by studying their internal kinematics using the MaNGA survey.
- Analysis being done using Python based code with heavy use of machine learning algorithms such as DB scan and PCA from the sci-kit learn library
- Unique use of PCA which focused more on using the actual PC vectors rather than using them as the basis in a PC profile plot
- Project Supervisor: Dr. Mubdi Rahman (Dunlap Institute)

# Work Experience \_\_\_\_\_

### **Tutor Doctor/Independent**

Toronto, Canada
May 2018 - Present

MATH & PHYSICS TUTOR

- Tutored various high school students in senior level math and physics courses
- Improved my communication/collaborative skills in order to ensure I was communicating the content as clearly as possible to my students

**Donorworx** Toronto, Canada

CHARITY FUNDRAISER, TEAM LEADER POSITION

Apr. 2019 - Sept. 2019

- Canvassed various neighborhoods in order to collect monthly donations for non-profits such as: Sistering, World Vision, and Save the Children
- Lead teams of fundraisers (8-15 people), was in charge of organizing which streets they went to, tracking their progress and making sure everything was running smoothly
- Improved my leadership skills as I was in a position where I coached fellow fundraisers. Lead team huddles to energize the team and ensure our day was as successful as possible
- Enriched my public speaking skills and learned how to present complicated topics in a concise and engaging manner

### Presentations and Talks

SURP Poster Fair Toronto, Canada

SCIENCE POSTER PRESENTATION

Aug. 13 2021

- Presented poster that summarized summer research in fair were all members of the astronomy department at the University of Toronto were invited to attend. **Won top poster award**
- Project poster can be seen by clicking here

#### **SDSS Collaboration Meeting 2021**

Baltimore, USA

PRESENTER IN DATA 1 SERIES AND LIGHTING TALK 1 SERIES

Aug. 11 2021

 Presented research that was in the paper preparation stage. Talk title: Exploring the Link Between the Star Formation History and the Morphology of Galaxies in SDSS-IV MaNGA. Hosted by John Hopkins University, for conference details click here

# **Education**

### **University of Toronto**

Toronto, Canada HONS. BSc. IN ASTRONOMY AND PHYSICS Sept. 2017 - Jun. 2021

- Math minor and Philosophy Minor
- · Achieved cGPA of 3.60 (A-) across all astrophysics based courses, including 4.0 GPA in undergraduate thesis

## **Extracurricular**

#### Languages

• Fluent in English and Spanish. Rudimentary ability to speak and read French. Currently learning Japanese, very basic ability to understand

#### **Technology**

- Take joy in playing around with various software applications/code on computers and other devices to optimize my experience
- Enjoy understanding computer hardware and how it functions, built my own desktop computer